<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. Tillam's account examined. Or, A brief reply to his unchristian account of some passages of Providence By a friend to truth, and to Mr. Tillam's own soul, if God have not sealed him down under hardness of heart. Written for the sake of such poor honest souls in Colchester, and the parts adjacent, as are misled through his inchantments.</title>
            <author>Weld, Thomas, 1590?-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96172</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1268aA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231931</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897094</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897094</idno>
            <idno type="VID">137293</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96172)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 137293)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2468:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. Tillam's account examined. Or, A brief reply to his unchristian account of some passages of Providence By a friend to truth, and to Mr. Tillam's own soul, if God have not sealed him down under hardness of heart. Written for the sake of such poor honest souls in Colchester, and the parts adjacent, as are misled through his inchantments.</title>
                  <author>Weld, Thomas, 1590?-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 30, [2]   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In answer to Thomas Tillam's "A Christian account". Title untraced.</note>
                  <note>With a final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tillam, Thomas. --  Christian account --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Providence and government of God --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Truth --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:137293:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>TILLAM'S</hi> ACCOUNT EXAMINED, OR, A brief Reply to his unchriſtian Account of ſome paſſages of <hi>Providence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a Friend to Truth, and to Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi>'s own Soul, if GOD have not ſealed him down under hardneſs of heart.</p>
            <p>Written for the ſake of ſuch poor honeſt ſouls in <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> and the parts adjacent, as are Miſled through his Inchantments.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Should not the multitude of words be anſwered? and ſhould a man full of talk be juſtified?</p>
               <p>Should thy lyes make men hold their peace? and when thou mockeſt, ſhall no man make thee aſhamed?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Joh 11.2, 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Author, 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:137293:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:137293:2"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Eradventure, a Reply to Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi>'s pretended <hi>Chriſtian Account</hi> was long ſince expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but, upon ſufficient reaſon, a delay was made. It was ſome time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the parties moſt concerned in it (living at a diſtance) could know of his Pamphlet: But chiefly, after it was drawn up, it was judged fit, by ſome intereſſed in the buſines, to lay it aſide, hoping that his folly would be made manifeſt enough by his own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; which indeed is already done in great part, eſpecially to pious and prudent Chriſtians; And, I doubt not, but it will be diſcovered more and more daily. But in regard of his <hi>vain triumphs,</hi> and becauſe there are many weak, harmleſs, and well mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing people in danger of being further delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by him, it is now reſolved to preſent <hi>the Man</hi> to the open view of the world, that
<pb facs="tcp:137293:3"/>his untruths, ſcandals, and dangerous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns may make all more cautious whom they confide in, and depend upon, in ſo great concernment as that of <hi>Religion.</hi> Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this, and other accounts (Reader) thou ſhalt here find ſuch a diſcovery of Mr. <hi>T. T.</hi> written, not out of envy to him, but pitty to others miſled by him, as (I hope) will make thee ſenſible of the bottom of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in coming to <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to be guided to, by a <hi>hand of Providence;</hi> but upon peruſall of this, I believe, thou wilt find, it was rather a <hi>Plot</hi> than a <hi>Providence,</hi> being the laſt adventure of a neceſsitated perſon, that muſt ſhift for himſelf ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, diſcarded by thoſe in the <hi>North</hi> who firſt gave him credit, and having his 40<abbr>l.</abbr> 
               <hi>per ann.</hi> withdrawn by the Commiſsioners there. Yet no doubt a <hi>providence</hi> it was too, but ſuch a one as that of <hi>Colchester</hi> Siege, which prevented the ſuffering of other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces when the Enemy was garriſon'd there. And I wiſh, that as that party had their laſt conſiderable motion terminated within the walls of <hi>Colchester</hi> (the adjacent parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:137293:3"/>ſufficiently alarumed by their being there) ſo alſo Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> may make your miſerable Town the ultimate ſtage of his progreſs. 'Tis pitty other places ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be troubled with ſuch a gueſt as <hi>ſets the houſe on fire where ever he comes,</hi> making it his buſineſs to divide and ſow diſcord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Brethren; By which (if there were nothing elſe) it may be eaſily gathered of what fraternitie he is. It is abundantly known what their Religion is, whoſe aim is <hi>diviſion;</hi> knowing how to retire into uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among themſelves, and meet together in one centre, though the lines drawn from it ſtand at a diſtance in the circumference. Doubtleſs Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi>'s ſlighting Mr. <hi>Prin</hi>'s charge (of his being a Papiſt) is a Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece: 'Tis more policity for Mr. <hi>T.</hi> to contemn than anſwer ſo fair a probability. His own acknowledgement that hee has been a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> together with his Romiſh trinkets, Extreme Unction, Waſhing of feet, pretences to infallibility (the choiceſt Jewels in the Popes Triple Crown) for all he ſpeaks muſt be taken as the Oracles of
<pb facs="tcp:137293:4"/>God, without any conſulting others, though never ſo pious and prudent; theſe things I ſay may ſtrongly perſwade a ſober man to ſuſpect a <hi>papist in the bottom.</hi> But I ſhall not judge him, Reader, let me only perſwade thee to lay aſide prejudice, and thou ſhalt here find Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> paſsing judgement up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf; for moſt of the particulars charged upon him in this book, are no other but ſuch as dropt from his own Pen or Tongue; and therfore, if any wrong be done him, he may thank himſelf for it. But I ſhall hold thee no longer in the Porch; if thou wilt know more, read further; let thine own eyes be thy informers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That which follows is a Letter written by Mr</hi> Robert Eaton <hi>to a friend of his, which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired him to print.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:137293:4"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy and endeared Friend;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Having at laſt met with Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi>'s Pamphlet, falſly intitled, <hi>A Chriſtian Account,</hi> I thought good in the firſt place to give you an account of him, and then of thoſe paſſages in his Pamphlet which relate to me. This <hi>Tillam,</hi> who is not aſhamed to call the <hi>Cenſures</hi> which the Church &amp; People of God have paſſed upon him, <hi>The Trials of his grace,</hi> was for a ſhort time an Aporthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary, but fince having aſſumed to be an Anabaptiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Miniſter, by reaſon of his <hi>fasticuſneſs, pride,</hi> and <hi>turbulency of Spirit,</hi> hath been like a ball of Wild-fire toſſed from one end of the Nation to another; ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering his <hi>peſlilent errours</hi> with very great <hi>impudence</hi> and <hi>boldneſs</hi> in every place where he hath come. Now though I had heard in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> and other places (before my removal from <hi>Dedham</hi>) of the dangerous conditions of this man, and what diſturbance he had made in ſeveral places, in venting and propagating his Errours, yet now I am more fully certified of the truth of thoſe things which there I heard.</p>
            <p>For brevity ſake I ſhall only give you an account of Mr. <hi>Samuel Eaton</hi>'s, who is Paſtor of the Church of <hi>Duckenfield</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> before whom one of Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi>'s cauſes was examined, and by whom Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi>'s Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication out of the Church at <hi>Wrexam</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared juſt and regular: Mr. <hi>Sam. Eaton</hi>'s words are theſe, Mr. <hi>Tillam was excommunicated firſt by the Church at</hi> Wrexam, <hi>and afterwards his Excommunication was found and declared juſt by the Church at</hi> Duckenfield, <hi>The
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:137293:5"/>cauſes of his Excommunication were ſeveral; among others were theſe; The proof of ſeveral untruths told by him, intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable pride, together with a viſible deſign to divide the Church, &amp;c. but that he withdrew himſelf, and that his withdrawing (as Mr.</hi> Tillam <hi>excuſes the matter) was the cauſe of his Excommunication, is utterly falſe, and a meer evaſion; fir they were fully reſolved to caſt him out before he did withdraw himſelf, and he withdrew himſelf purpoſely to evade the ſentence: And many that were his Diſciples, and Rebaptized by him, when they heard things laid open, were ſatisfied to the juſtneſſe of the ſentence pronounced againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far Mr. <hi>Sam. Eaton</hi> gave me an account of him: Now whether a man ſo eminent as Mr. <hi>Sam. Eaton</hi> (in a buſineſs where he can have no by-reſpects) is to be believed, or Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> (one cauſe of whoſe Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication was lying) let all men judge.</p>
            <p>As for that Church of <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> which he ſo much magnifies in his book, I ſhall not meddle with them, only this I ſhall ſay, that ſome of them, though under the Ordinance (as their expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is) for which Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> hath, and doth ſhew ſo much zeal, and therefore more likely to favour Mr. <hi>Tillam's</hi> cauſe; Yet (I ſay) ſome of them doe diſown him, as not fit to be communicated withall; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have told me, that he is diſowned by their whole Church; yea ſome of that <hi>ſweet ſociety</hi> (as Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> calls them) do ſuſpect him to be a <hi>Jeſuit;</hi> and ſeveral grounds they have of their ſuſpition, as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have related to me.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe he hath acknowledged that once he was a Papiſt; and again he hath confeſſed (as ſome of them have told me) that he hath been at <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:137293:5"/>
            <p> Secondly, they have obſerved him to deliver doctrines in favour of Juſtification by Works: And truly though he ſo ſlightly paſs over that which Mr. <hi>Prin</hi> charges him withall, yet, I think, he ought, there being ſo much ground of ſuſpition, to have laboured more for his vindication in that particular, than meerly to ſay, <hi>It is a groſs ſlander.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as for thoſe paſſages in his Pamphlet which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to me; Though I have underſtood by ſeveral per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that he hath not only a falſe tongue, but alſo a bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen face, yet I conceive he would never have been ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent as to have uttered ſuch a reproach without the leaſt ground, but that he hoped it would never have come to my knowledge, I being now ſo far remote. But I have now at laſt providentially obtained a ſight of his Pamphlet, and for my own vidication, I ſhall give an account of all that paſſed betwixt him and me, whence he hath taken an hint to forg all thoſe reproaches he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleth upon me.</p>
            <p>I being occaſionally with Mr. <hi>Malyn,</hi> Secretary to the Lord Protector, and with Mr. <hi>Wakering,</hi> and ſome other Gentlemen at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> there was mention made of this ſame <hi>Tillam,</hi> and the Inſtrument whereby he was autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized to preach in any vacant place, which Mr. <hi>Malyn</hi> hearing of, ſaid, He was very confident he never had any ſuch Inſtrument granted him by the Protector: And that there never was any granted him, he told me, and ſome Gentlemen there, after that he had been with his Highneſs the Lord Protector to enquire about it. Yea he added further, that an Order ſhould iſſue out to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend him. What I then heard, I related to ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, whom I occaſionally had ſome diſcourſe withal concerning Mr. <hi>Tillam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some weeks after Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> came to me, charging me
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:137293:6"/>that I ſhould ſay hisInſtrument was conterfeited: To whom I anſwered it was not ſo: But nevertheleſs what I had heard, and from whom I heard it, as I had told o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſo now alſo I would acquaint him, and all that is above-mentioned touching the diſcourſe with Mr. <hi>Malyn</hi> concerning him and his Inſtrument, I related to him; and added, that if any wrong were done him, he muſt ſeek to Mr. <hi>Malyn,</hi> Secretary to the Lord Protector, for repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. Yet I further told him, if he would produce his Inſtrument, and if upon the ſight of it I ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that it was a reality, upon a Chriſtian Account I would tell thoſe perſons who heard the former relation from me, that I had ſince ſeen his Inſtrument, and that it was a real thing. Now that this is the truth and the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of all that which was ſaid by me, thoſe two emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Miniſters that Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> ſpeaks of in his Pamphlet (<hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hudſon</hi> of <hi>Capel,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> of <hi>Aſsington</hi>) wil atteſt. And if this be the truth, and thoſe fore-named Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters wil give teſtimony to it (as they ſay they wil) then either both I and they are lyars, and ſtirred up by Satan, the Father of lyes (as Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> expreſſes it) or elſe Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> (who for lying, among other things, was Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate, and ſo given up to the Father of lyes) hath not yet repented of, nor is delivered from that ſin, but ſeems now rather to have habituated himſelfe unto it, as I ſhall make appear by a paſſage or two in his book, which ſavours much of that lying ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Not to ſtand to ſhew how little ground Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> had, upon my relating of what I heard, to bottom thoſe expreſſions of his upon, (<hi>viz. That I calumniated him, that I falſly accuſed him, that I confidently affirmed, that his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument was conterfeited</hi>) little untruths are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be taken notice of, when they come from
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:137293:6"/>Mr. <hi>Tillam's</hi> either Tongue or Pen.</p>
            <p>But ſuch a <hi>Forchead of braſſe,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>Conſcience of brawn</hi> has he, that he is not afraid, nor aſhamed to ſay, <hi>after my falſhood was diſcovered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when was this <hi>diſcovery</hi> made? in what place? and before what witneſſes? He that helped him to make that (I mean his Father of lyes) muſt either help him with another, or elſe this will appear to be, as it is, <hi>a loud one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> ſaith, <hi>That I (with two eminent Miniſters) laboured for peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To labour for peace I know is a Chriſtian duty, yet not with an Excommunicate perſon. And how I and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boveſaid Miniſters laboured for peace with Mr. <hi>Tillam,</hi> you ſhall judge by that which follows.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall ask Mr. <hi>Tillam,</hi> whether I went from <hi>Dedham</hi> to him at <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> or he came from <hi>Colcheſter</hi> to me at <hi>Dedham?</hi> If he came to me, hitherto Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> (and not I) laboured and took the pains.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> was at <hi>Dedham,</hi> whether I ſought after, and went to him, or he to me? If he to me, then hitherto alſo Mr. <hi>Tillam,</hi> and not I, laboured and took the pains.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, after Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> was at my houſe, whether I laboured any further, or took any more pains with him, than ſpeaking the words rehearſed before? Indeed this I did, having heard that Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> had been convicted of, and excommunicated for lying, among other things (though then I had not certain proof of it, as now I have) I deſired thoſe two fore-named Miniſters, being then at my houſe, to hear what ſhould paſs in diſcourſe betwixt us, leſt Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> ſhould afterwards (according to his manner) beſpatter me, as he had done ſome others
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:137293:7"/>with groſs untruths, and his Pamphlet may evidence I had good reaſon ſo to do.</p>
            <p>But that <hi>I laboured for peace myſelfe,</hi> further than is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed before, or that I ever deſired either of thoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Miniſters to labour for peace on my behalf, is falſe, and it comes from Mr. <hi>Tillam's</hi> Father of lyes.</p>
            <p>In the third page of his book he mentions a <hi>project of mine,</hi> what it is I know not, unleſs it be this honeſt one, <hi>That an Impoſtor who grows worſe and worſe, deceiving, and being deceived, may be diſcovered.</hi> But what ever project I had, this I diſcern to be one in Mr. <hi>Tillam,</hi> who that he may breed prejudices in his Diſciples againſt the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of thoſe that bear witneſs againſt him, uſeth to ſay, <hi>they are his enemies;</hi> as if all thoſe perſons, that in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parts of this Nation, have teſtified againſt Mr. <hi>Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam</hi> and his waies (whereof ſome are eminent for learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and religion) were acted from a principle of envy and malice againſt him, and not from zeal to God and his truth.</p>
            <p>But that that Great untruth (<hi>viz. an eminent diſcovery of my Falſhood</hi>) may not be thought a ſlip of his Pen, but a deliberate birth, formed by the Father of lyes, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats it, and puts an <hi>emphaſis</hi> upon it, page 3. (not dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any falſhood, ſo eminently diſcovered) all that I ſhall ſay to this, is onely thus much; That I never had any diſcourſe with Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> in all my life, but that which was mentioned before in my own houſe at <hi>Ded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> when thoſe two Miniſters with ſome others were there; And if thoſe two Reverend Miniſters (Mr. <hi>Hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>) will not teſtifie that it is eminently falſe, that there was any falſhood diſcovered in me at that time, then let not onely this, but all the reſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:137293:7"/>that Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> is charged withall, be ſaid at my door.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall not any further trouble my ſelf with him; God (I hope) will in ſhort time lay him open, what he is, that he may <hi>proceed no further</hi> inſeducing ſimple and unwary ſoules.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your affectionate Friend</hi> Robert Eaton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <p>
               <hi>The following ſheets were done by another hand; in the Vindication of Mr.</hi> Hammond: <hi>when you ſhall find a ſatisfactory Anſwer to the Reminder of Mr.</hi> Tillam's <hi>abuſive Pamphlet.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:137293:8"/>
            <head>Mr. Tillam's Account Examined.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>R. <hi>Tillam's</hi> glozing Pamphlet within theſe very few dayes coming to my hands, and perceiving (with great grief of heart) his old ſpirit of <hi>pride, vain-glory, boaſting, lying,</hi> and <hi>ſlandering,</hi> tunning through the veins thereof; and underſtanding that Mr. <hi>Hammond</hi> (who with a breath could have blown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all his vapourings, if he had been willing to have ſtirred in his own cauſe) not willing to meddle with ſuch an incurable creature; hereupon my ſpirit was drawn forth (not ſo much for his ſake, as to undeceive ſuch ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt hearts as are abuſed by his hypocriſie) to pull off his Mask, and let them ſee the man in his proper ſhape.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he is a man <hi>boared in the ear, branded and stig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matized in the forehead,</hi> by the moſt godly perſons where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he yet came, when they once knew him well (though at the firſt, through his fawning and glozing carriage they were for a while deluded by him) For,</p>
            <p>Firſt, he is with one conſent given up to Satan by the whole Church of <hi>Wrexam,</hi> which though he labour to ſhuffle off, yet the reſtimony of one twenty godly men (for ſo they will be proved to be in ſpight of all his aſperſions) (when ſober men hold the ſcales) ſhall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:137293:8"/>over ballance the ſingle teſtimony of one man, in his own cauſe, who is a Lyar upon record.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when his caſe was judiciouſly heard and ſcanned by ſuch godly Elders, and the Church of <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> to which himſelfe appealed, they concluded the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure juſt, and rolled the ſame ſtone upon him in thſe words (as Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> himſelf writes, <hi>p. 6.</hi>) <hi>That he was to be looked upon as neither an Elder, nor a Member of the Church of</hi> Wrexmham, <hi>but to be left to the world as a man without.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, then after this, Converſing with the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt-Church in <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> he ſo carries himſelf (though at the firſt, <hi>who but Mr,</hi> Tillam) that they preſented to the Church at <hi>London,</hi> twelve ſeveral Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les againſt him.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, he alſo falls ſo foul with the three Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational Miniſters in <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> (Mr. <hi>weld,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Durant,</hi> whom God and his Servants are pleaſed gratiouſly to own) that they are forced to vindicate themſelves to the world in print (which they never did againſt any man before) to paint him out to the life.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, after this (as if he ſtudied to imitate <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> To have his hand againſt every man, and procure every mans hand againſt him) he breaks with the Church at <hi>London</hi> (in whoſe very boſom he lay for a while, till they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived his frame) who caſt him off with much indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as (ſtill) it appears by his own confeſſion in his book, <hi>p.</hi> 19. (for we have moſt of all theſe things from his own words.)</p>
            <p>Sixthly, at laſt his own Church at <hi>Hexam</hi> (ſuch was his carriage towards them) falls into two pieces; and one part of the two, diſcards him. Now, if theſe be not Black marks, or Fleſh-brands; if theſe things will not prove him to goe out from all places [<hi>like a ſnuff</hi>]
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:137293:9"/>which words he ſo pittifully ſnuffs at, Let wiſe and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber men judge.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Obſerve all along his courſe of life, and his Book alſo, that whereas all Godly men in Scripture, and our own experience, ſo ſuffer uſually from the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Grace, wicked and ungodly men which is an honorable thing, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.10, 11. <hi>For the Spirit of God and Glory reſteth upon ſuch.</hi>) Now this mans caſe is quite otherwiſe: For, ſtill, he is oppoſed, and conteſted withall, and rejected by the Godly, yea, and moſt uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>moſt eminent for godlineſs,</hi> in all places whereſoever he comes, at <hi>wrexam, Cheſhire, Newcaſtle, London,</hi> and now at <hi>Colcheſter;</hi> i. e. by godly Chriſtians, faithful Miniſters, Paſtor, Teachers, Elders, yea, whole Churches, and that in the <hi>gheſt degree of Cenſures</hi> that ever Jeſus Chriſt ordained in his Churches, <hi>Excommunication it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again, whereas other godly men ſuffer as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, for <hi>well doing</hi> (which is a bleſſed thing) this man is ſtill buffered, not for his good deeds, but for his faults, ſcandals, pride, ſlanders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And.</p>
            <p>(Which is exceedingly to be noted) good men uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are oppoſed and fought againſt by men of differring judgements and practices from themſelves; as Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational men by Presbyterial, Paedobaptiſts by Antipae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dobaptiſts, Orthodox by Arminians, Socinians, and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants by Papiſts; but this man (as if he were <hi>born to ſtrife</hi>) is ſtill oppoſed by men of his own judgement and practice in Doctrine and Diſcipline. Were not the Church of <hi>Wrexam,</hi> and that of <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> and the three Miniſters of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> of his own judgement and practice in point of Diſcipline? Did not the Anabaptiſt Church nof <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> and that of <hi>London,</hi> jump with him in point of Baptiſm? Yet he is a man not onely <hi>diſguſted</hi> by all
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:137293:9"/>theſe, but one <hi>not ſufferable to abide among them,</hi> and <hi>out</hi> he muſt as an incorrigible perſon, without reconciliation; which how clear it ſpeaks in point of <hi>his intollerable tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulency of ſpirit,</hi> and what an alarum it rings in all their ears who are miſled through his ſubtle inſinuations, I leave to all men to judge.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A common Lyar is generally accounted a <hi>vile perſon, a ſon of Belial,</hi> one of the baſeſt among men; but to gather up all his groſs lies and ſlanders were too heavy a task; for certainly he hath driven an <hi>old Trade</hi> therein: For,</p>
            <p>Firſt, he was caſt out of <hi>Wrexam</hi> Church for lying, as one principal crime among others.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he is rejected by the Church at <hi>London</hi> for making and maintaining a lye; ſee his own words, <hi>page 19. It was concluded</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> himſelf) <hi>that I lyed, and they preſently declared a withdrawing from me</hi> (with theſe words added, which are) <hi>he hath grievouſly ſinned againſt the Rule of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>Col. 3.9. Lye not one to anther: Wherefore we have put him away from us, and ſhall have no communion with him, that he may be aſhamed.</hi> This from his own words; and this was done deliberately, after much ſcanning, by a whole Church.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, there are many manifeſt lyes in this his book, as, <hi>that Mr.</hi> Hammond <hi>was Vicar of</hi> Newcaſtle (which he writes to diſgrace Mr. <hi>Hammond</hi>) whereas he is only Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturer and Teacher to a Congregational Church, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely refuſed to be Vicar, which Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> cannot but know, being ſo oft converſant in <hi>Newcaſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, another abhominable lye againſt that Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Man, in theſe words, <hi>whither have thoſe ſurſeiting feaſts of</hi> Newcaſtle (ſaith he) <hi>tranſported Mr.</hi> Hammond? <hi>how ſtrangely have thoſe luxurious banques increaſed choler in this corpulent Gentleman?</hi> For, beſides the odious contempt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:137293:10"/>in the manner of his writing which he caſts upon this faithfull ſervant of Chriſt (ſo much beloved and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Saints) he moſt impudently and palpably ſlanders him for intemperance; for all <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that though Mr. <hi>Hammond</hi> be often and earneſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited to Feaſts, yet he hath abſolutely refuſed (to avoid all occaſions) to come at <hi>any feaſt,</hi> great or ſmall, to one or other, for theſe two years together, except at one time that was unavoydable.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, he boldly vaunts, that God made himſelf an inſtrument of detecting the falſe Jew, wherein (beſides that vain-glorious vapouring, in aſſuming to himſelf what is not due) he tells a moſt manifeſt falſhhood; for it's notoriouſly known to Mr. <hi>Goe. Dauſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> Mr. <hi>Durant,</hi> and others, that he did what he could when they were about convincing the falſe Jew, to defend him and harden his heart, till they were all grieved and aſhamed at his practice.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, another falſhood, that Mr. <hi>Hammond</hi> was baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled in the diſpute about Baptiſm; which impudency of his is <hi>ſtupendious;</hi> for above a hundred perſons preſent will witneſs the exceeding freedom of Mr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> whoſe arguments were as a Rod held over him all the diſpute, and that Mr. <hi>Tillam,</hi> to his utter confuſion (if he could tell how to be aſhamed) was ſo non-pluſs'd, and baffled to purpoſe, that one of his own party was driven to confeſs it, &amp; to chide him off, &amp; take up the bucklers, whiles all the time after Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> ſate dumb; which calls to mind a ſeventh lye; He told Mr. <hi>George Hodſhan,</hi> when he came firſt into the North, that he was for the Baptiſm of the Infants of Beleevers, when it manifeſtly appears, he was at the ſame time an Anabaptiſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>per me Geo. Hodſhan.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:137293:10"/>
            <p> Laſtly, for a full conviction of his lyes, ſee the <hi>bundle of urtruths,</hi> written by the <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> Miniſters againſt Mr. <hi>Tillam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this Lying is ſuch a ſin as it makes a man ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like God, into whoſe image all his children are caſt, and ſo like the devil, who is the <hi>Father of lyes,</hi> and ſo unlike the Saints, who are a generation that <hi>will not lye,</hi> Iſa. 63.9. that it deſerves the heavieſt cenſure of Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15. <hi>Without</hi> (the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) <hi>ſhall be dogs, and whoremonges, and murtherers, and idolaters, and whoſoever loveth and maketh lies.</hi> See (Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi>) what copeſmates Lyars are matched withall, and what is their cenſure; and yet you are angry with the Church at <hi>London</hi> for rejecting you for lying, and giving you no warning, whereas the Rule it ſelf (you ſee) gives no ſuch direction for any warning; but it being once proved (as it ſeems the <hi>London</hi> Church averred) you were to be preſently ſent without among the dogs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. obſerve his proud boaſting, and vaunting high language, almoſt in every page of his book (and indeed all his writings and actings doe fulſomly tang of that ſpirit) In the front of his book he begins, <hi>Thanks to my Lord and King, who hath enabled me, ſo that he counted me faithfull, putting me into the Miniſtery.</hi> Which are the words of the greateſt Apoſtle on earth, and that in the height of his zeal; yet this man dares apply them to himſelf, which I beleeve never any Miniſter, that knows himſelf, dares noce doe. So that he is (if you will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve him) an <hi>able Minister,</hi> a <hi>faithfull Miniſter,</hi> and, as he ſaith afterwards, a <hi>welling Miniſter,</hi> and a Miniſter that <hi>labours with his whole ſoul in the work;</hi> whereas humble ſpirits are ever fearfull to think highly of themſelves, much more to lift up themſelves in print, by <hi>vapouring
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:137293:11"/>tearms, and high titles.</hi> Furthermore, you have him ever and anon vaunting of the multitude of his hearers and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, &amp; great ſucceſs in his Miniſtery in every place, that he could gather a Church of Saints in a years ſpace in ſuch or ſuch place where he came; which (by the way) ſhews his doctrine and practice very ſuitable to carnall hearts, that can ſo eaſily take with him in all places where hee comes, whereas the doctrine of the beſt Miniſter under heaven is ſo croſs to corrupt nature, that it cannot be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted; but his doctrine and opinions goe glib down, and can bring in ſouls <hi>tiick and threefold;</hi> 'tis but <hi>touch and take.</hi> And I cannot omit how often this poor man boaſTs in high language of his ſufferings, and calls them <hi>ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings for Chriſts ſake, and for his names ſake,</hi> and all <hi>in obedience to him;</hi> whereas (preſumptuous man) thou maiſt know, it was (all along) for thy <hi>faults, ſcandals, lyes, turbulency, faction</hi> and <hi>diſembling</hi> from the firſt till now. Was it for Chriſts ſake thou wert given up to Satan by the Church of <hi>Wrexam?</hi> Was it for thy good deeds thou wert con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the Church in <hi>Cheſhire?</hi> Was it for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Chriſt that the Church in <hi>London</hi> roſe up againſt thee (and the three Miniſters in <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> writ againſt thee?) was it nor for a lye maintained againſt ſo many evidences? and haſt thou the face to father all thy wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched dealings on Chriſt? wil he maintain thee in a courſe of ſin, and crown thee for it? what tender heart can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt ſuch impudency and hypocriſie?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Obſerve what <hi>contempt, ſcorns,</hi> and baſe <hi>calumnies</hi> he (all along his book) caſts out again all that ſtand in his way, be they never ſo holy, never ſo many; be they <hi>godly Saints, Miniſters, whole Churches,</hi> all is one, if they ſpeak or a &amp; againſt him, the ſparkles of his anger (in a vile contemptuous manner) ſhall fly in their faces; this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:137293:11"/>is the very ſpirit of his Book. So (like the Dragon) he ſpews out whole floods of contempt, to drown them and their reputations if he could; to inſtance but in two or three particulars. 1. How ſhamefully doth he reproach the whole Church of <hi>Wrexam,</hi> that caſt him out, and the one and twenty Members, as if they were the vileſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons on earth (but who will beleeve him, they being known godly men?) and all this to juſtifie himſelf, and avoyd the dint of their conſure, as <hi>page</hi> 9, 10. at large? 2. Then again, how he reproaches the Church at <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle,</hi> becauſe they articled againſt him, <hi>page</hi> 19. 3. Then when <hi>London</hi> Church Excommunicated him, ſee his ſhamefull reproaching of them, as <hi>acting irregularly, and againſt light of conſcience;</hi> and what not? No marvel ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if he reproach Mr. <hi>Weld,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> Mr. <hi>Eaton, Hugh Prichard</hi> (theſe are but ſingle perſons) when he flies (like a waſp) in the face of whole Churches; and (that which is under this head remarkable) <hi>i. e.</hi> that all ſuch as bear witneſs againſt him, he <hi>falls ſoul</hi> upon them, as <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious perſons,</hi> as if there were <hi>no evil at all in him to teſtifie againſt;</hi> no, no, <hi>it's only the good they ſaw in him, his good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, the attendance on his Miniſtry, and Gods bleſſing on his labours,</hi> theſe are the things, the good things in him (as he would fain perſwade the world) they envy. <hi>when I preached</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in</hi> Cheſhire, <hi>I ſaw the power of God, and</hi> (then adds) <hi>there I incurred Mr.</hi> Eaton's <hi>diſpleaſure.</hi> Why dareſt thou ſay, that holy Man (Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi>) <hi>was diſpleaſed at the power of God in thee?</hi> And within two lines after he ſpeaks as bad of the Church of <hi>Wrexam; The Church of</hi> Wrexam (ſaith he) <hi>was troubled at my ſucceſſe.</hi> Now to make men envious perſons at the grace of God in others, is to make them the very <hi>devils eldest Sons,</hi> and himſelf muſt needs be <hi>God</hi> (or in Gods place) to judge their very
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:137293:12"/>hearts, that it was <hi>Gods grace in him</hi> that moved them to bear witneſs againſt him. Whither will the venome and malice of this mans ſpirit carry him?</p>
            <p n="6">6. As he caſts down to Hell almoſt all that oppoſe him, ſo he lifts up to Heaven all that ſide with him, or favour him in his way; witneſs his <hi>extreme flattery</hi> of the Magiſtrates in <hi>Coldeſter</hi> that favour him; witneſs alſo his high elevating thoſe three men at <hi>Hexam</hi> that certified for him (and there were but three in all) and how eaſie a matter it is for any man to bring three men in a whole County to atteſt any thing in a mans behalf, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe what he himſelf ſhall draw, and bring to them to ſubſcribe, all men know. Yet, alaſs! ſome of us know what pittifull men ſome of thoſe three are, whom he ſets our, as if the moſt eminent in the whole County. Alas, alas, the man dares ſay any thing, bad or good, of any man to ſerve his own turn. It this man be not <hi>a dawber, a ſcraper with his nails</hi> for mens favours, an <hi>inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting flatterer</hi> for his own ends, I never knew any. He will verifie what Mr. <hi>Hammond</hi> writ of him; <hi>He is</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Hammond</hi>) <hi>the moſt fawning man till you diſcover him; and, then, the moſt looſe-tongued man in reviling.</hi> Is it not juſt ſo?</p>
            <p n="7">7. Mark his <hi>railing:</hi> The <hi>poyſon of Alps is under his lips,</hi> his mouth and ſtile is full of <hi>curſing and bitterneſſe;</hi> for theſe are his uſual tearms, <hi>Men ſtirred up by the Devil, Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, Rigid ones, Falſe lyars, Men born from beneath, Sons of the earth, Abſoloms, Joabs, Whited ſepulchres, Full of horrid hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie and iniquity; that wofull hypocrite, that proud diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church, that proud ſcornfull</hi> Haman, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe are his expreſſions, and that againſt any, even againſt the moſt godly and eminent in grace, that doe but oppoſe him. And, though to write, or ſpeak ſuch things of a man,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:137293:12"/>when matters are proved upon Record againſt him by a cloud of witneſſes (as thoſe things are which I hold forth againſt him, as <hi>lying, boaſting, vaunting, &amp;c.</hi> which I have proved, either directly from his own words, or the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of whole Churches) although this (I ſay) be juſt againſt himſelf, and no wrong donetherein, yet for him to belch out ſuch vile reproaches, when no juſt cauſe is given, ſuch language in him is plain <hi>railing,</hi> whereas gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him his own tearms, when matters are proved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, is but righteous dealing.</p>
            <p n="8">8. It's an uſual thing with him throughout his whole book, to ſet <hi>his own ſingle testimony</hi> againſt all that conteſt with him; be his Adverſaries never ſo holy, never ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, yet his own bare word muſt paſs for current, againſt the ſubſcription of the one and twenty Members, yea the whole Church of <hi>Wrexam,</hi> the Elders of the Church in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> the Baptized Church in <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> the three Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Congregational Churches there, the whole Church at <hi>London, &amp;c.</hi> whereas <hi>Moſes, Paul,</hi> and Chriſt himſelf tell us, that in the mouth of two or three wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes every truth ſhall be eſtabliſhed; here are three, ten, twenty, yea whole Churches, and yet all are falſe, and deluded, he only ſpeaks the truth, himſelf being wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. If this be not the very ſpirit of his book, let any man that has not forfeited his reaſon, judge. And from whence (do we think) comes this, from Heaven, or from Hell?</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>His Inſtability</hi> is notorious. He was once, by his own confeſſion a Papiſt, then a Proteſtant again (if he may be believed) (though ſome of his own friends doe ſhrewdly ſuſpect him to be ſtill a Papiſt in his heart, and that his turning <hi>Church-divider</hi> at <hi>Wrexam,</hi> and <hi>Dipper</hi> afterwards, was but a turning every ſtone, and trying e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:137293:13"/>ſide, to ſee where he might beſt advance a Popiſh deſign) at laſt, as if weary of every thing, he falls now to the <hi>Holy kiſs, Waſhing the Saints feet, Annointing with Oyl</hi> (ſome ſay to ſix Sacraments) to <hi>denyal of the Trinity of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Original ſin of Infants,</hi> &amp;c. When, and where will this man ſtop? Nay, ſo far is he deluded and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicated, that he calls this giddineſs in running out to unſound fancies, and dangerous opinions, <hi>obedience to Chriſt,</hi> pag. 13. And as he is weary of truth, ſo of all perſons, ſocieties, and places too, where ever he yet came. In the Church of <hi>Wrexam</hi> (ſo much admired by him at the firſt) he ſtayes but eighteen Months, and then it's ſuch a <hi>corrupt ſociety, that he is glad he is out of it.</hi> Then to <hi>Cheſhire</hi> he haſtens, there's the only Church, but he playes ſuch pranks there, that he is ſoon diſcovered. Then away into the South; from the South into the North he goes, <hi>Hexam</hi> is the place, and there he has a <hi>glorious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> (if ye will credit his report) (for ſtill all his Geeſe are Swans) But <hi>Hexam</hi> grows ſtale, the South is more deſirable, and <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> of all places of <hi>England,</hi> is the onely place; and there you ſhall have him as long as you of <hi>Colcheſter</hi> ſhall court him with applauſe, honour, &amp; liberal gifts (for want of which he was pitifully pined at <hi>Hexam</hi>) but as ſoon as you diſcover him, as others have done, you ſhall find him indeed, to goe out like a ſnuff; for do but run through the ſtory of his life, or read but his own Pamphlet, and you ſhall ſee how after a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while he has ſet fire on every place where he came, and run away by the light of it.</p>
            <p n="10">10. But, above all, his <hi>notorious abuſe of Scripture</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable, making the bleſſed Holy Ghoſt (the Author of it) to ſerve his luſt, and execute his revenge upon all ſuch as conteſt againſt his ſin; as if he himſelf were <hi>that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:137293:13"/>righteous one</hi> whom the Holy Ghoſt intended in thoſe Scriptures he quotes, to vindicate and maintain, be his cauſe never ſo bad, and to condemn all his oppoſers, be they never ſo holy and good; and to ſtrike at them as his moſt <hi>inveterate, incorrigible enemies, as Scribes, Phariſecs, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors of Chriſt, his Apoſtles, and Prophets:</hi> Do but peruſe a little ſome of the ſcriptures he cites, and ſee if he would not deſign his godly adverſaries to the bottomleſs pit, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.20, 21. <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.4, 5. <hi>Jer.</hi> 20, 10, 11. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.5. <hi>Acts</hi> 21.28. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.14. to 18. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.27, 28. What height of <hi>pride, arrogancy, impudency, malice,</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge</hi> this man is grown unto, I leave to godly tender hearts to judge. <hi>Is it a ſmall thing to grieve men, but wilt thou grieve my God alſo? Iſa.</hi> 7.13.</p>
            <p>Thus having given you a little taſt of the man (and truly but a little, for it were endleſs to print him out in all his lineaments) but by the Lyons paw you may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the proportion of all the other parts of the beaſt, I ſhall now proceed to wipe off ſuch aſperſions as he caſts without fear upon ſome dear ſervants of God in his Book, and leave all other things as not worth the while.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for Mr. <hi>Hammond</hi> (a man ſo eminently known, that he is above the reach of his ſlanderous pen) yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath ſo plainly laid him open to the world, he muſt be the mark for Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> to ſhoot his venemous arrows at: The cauſe was this (for Mr. <hi>Hammond</hi> upon this account hath been deſired to declare the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) who ſaith as followeth;</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="testimony">
               <body>
                  <p>That he with ſome others having diſcovered the Converſion of the Jew (whom Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> baptized, and ſo boaſted of) to be a cheat, publiſhed his Popiſh deſign to the world; but Mr. <hi>Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam</hi> perceiving the Romiſh plot and himſelf unvailed,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:137293:14"/>wrote a moſt falſe, ſlanderous Pamphlet againſt the diſcoverers, charging them with thirteen untruths, to which they replyed again, revealing the notorious ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, boaſting, ſlandering ſpirit of the man; to which Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> wrote another Reply, full of froth, lying, and folly, and ſent a Coppy of it in a braving way to Mr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> who returned him a ſharp Anſwer in a private Letter; and likewiſe told him, that Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> had given a large account of him, and withall ſent him a copy of Mr. <hi>Eaton's</hi> Letter, wherein Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares the righteous dealing of the Church of <hi>Wrexam</hi> againſt him (the ſubſtance of which you have in Mr. <hi>Robert Eaton's</hi> Letter) and that he turned Anabaptiſt upon it, and proved a great diſturber in thoſe parts.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Ita teſtor Sam. Hammond.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And was not all this plain dealing by Mr. <hi>Hammond?</hi> Thus things lay buried a great while, but at laſt Mr. <hi>Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam</hi> and Mr. <hi>Anderton</hi> having diſcovered the wickedneſs one of another, his Church at <hi>Hexam</hi> brake into two pieces: He then being diſcarded of all men, writes an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuating Letter to Mr. <hi>Hammond</hi> (as one begging his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour) who (out of the goodneſs of his diſpoſition, ready to forget all wrongs, upon the leaſt relenting of his worſt enemy) writes back again, that the thoughts of thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer quarrels were buried in his heart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Though at that very time, and when he came to this houſe, he ſtill dealt plainly, in reproving of him. But afterwards; Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> ſtill proceeding in his old ſtrain of ſcandal, Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence calling upon Mr. <hi>Hammond</hi> to declare his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him, he judged himſelf bound in conſcience to reveal him to ſuch as deſired an account of him, the Cauſe of God calling for it; and he doth appeal to the Great God, and any gracious ſpirit, whether there were
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:137293:14"/>
               <hi>diſſimulation, groſs diſſimulation and hypocriſie to amazement</hi> in all this? his Conſcience bears him witneſs that there was not. As for his charge of <hi>Feaſting,</hi> and calling Mr. <hi>Hammond Vicar of</hi> Newcaſtle (which are two evident falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods) it ſhews he hath not yet left his old trade of <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> His calling him <hi>proud Haman,</hi> with alluſion to his name, and <hi>Pope Boniface,</hi> in relation to that feature of face which God and Nature hath given him, ſpeaks a childiſh wanton ſinful ſpirit in Mr. <hi>Tillam,</hi> and let him know, that God will one day have an account of idle words.</p>
            <p>But he ſaith Mr. <hi>Hammond</hi> entertained him kindly, and added the courteſie of <hi>New wine:</hi> I ſay it was ill-beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on ſuch an ungratefull man, as quarrels with love; worthy the next time he comes to be thruſt out of doors among the beggars. All men that know Mr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> well know him to be a Gentleman, and full of courteſie to all that ſet foot over his threſhold; and he endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to conquer this unworthy man by kindneſs, eſpecially looking at him, as <hi>ſeeming now to repent of his former miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages,</hi> and is not this a trim requital? Again, his proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mr. <hi>Hammond</hi> ſo rigid againſt Anabaptiſts, is another great ſlander; for he never preacht againſt them; hee carries it moſt lovingly in all civill converſe towards them; his ſpirit and principle carry much moderation to men of different judgements. 'Tis true, he diſputed about the point of Baptiſm with Mr. <hi>Tillam,</hi> when Providence called him to it, wherein Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> was ſo ſilenced, that his denying of it ſince, hath demonſtrated to many who heard that diſpute, that he dares ſay any thing to ſave himſelf, and ſlander others. And for Mr. <hi>Hammond's</hi> moderation upon ſeveral accounts to Mr. <hi>Tillam,</hi> ſure his own conſcience will witneſs againſt him, if he deny it. yea, his own mouth hath often ſaid it, and here he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:137293:15"/>upbraids Mr. <hi>Hammond</hi> for it; yea he boldly tels the world, that <hi>Mr.</hi> Anderton's <hi>ejection was becauſe he called Mr.</hi> Hammond <hi>Pope</hi> Boniface, which (as Mr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> profeſſeth) he never knew Mr. <hi>Anderton</hi> ever ſaid ſo, till now he read it in Mr. <hi>Tillam's</hi> Pamphlet. But it's upon record he was ejected for <hi>Non-reſidency, and notorious Sabbath-breaking;</hi> ſo that it appears Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> will ſay any thing.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for Mr. <hi>Weld,</hi> he tels the world (<hi>pag.</hi> 7.20, 21.) he kindly invited him to his houſe in a Letter, with much ſeeming affection, and yet all but groſs diſſimulation. Since Mr. <hi>Tillam's</hi> book came out, Mr. <hi>Weld</hi> hath been conſulted withall, and deſired to write the truth of the buſineſs, whoſe very words again are theſe;</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>I muſt ſincerely profeſſe (being called thereto) that although I am not of the <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> Churches judgment of the unlawfulneſs of being ſent out to Preach by Commiſſioners and Miniſters, yet I cannot clear Mr. <hi>Tillam,</hi> nor vindicate his innocency, in denying that he had ſuch an order to Preach as the <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> Church charged him withall, <hi>pag.</hi> 20. For when I look into their three firſt Articles, <hi>pag.</hi> 16. wherein their charge of his receiving order from the Commiſſioners lyeth, I plainly ſee the full ſubſtance of their charge to be true in each Article.</p>
                  <p>For, whereas the Church ſay, 1. That he came to the Prieſt (they mean Miniſters) (by the way I could wiſh no ſuch word of contempt were uſed) this is truth, for he came to ſuch of us as were appointed to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min Miniſters to be ſent out to Preach, and told us, he came to us for that end, and we conferred with him in order thereunto.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Church ſaith, that he preached before them
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:137293:15"/>(that is, the Miniſters) for the tryal of his Gifts, this is as true; for he preached at <hi>Nicholas</hi> on a Thurſday Lecture, where divers of the Miniſters were preſent to hear his Gifts, and brought relation to the Commiſſioners, and the reſt of the Miniſters; and he was alſo tryed by perſonal examination be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Commiſſioners, this alſo is true.</p>
                  <p>3. That he was by the Propagators and Miniſters ſent to preach at <hi>Hexam,</hi> and by an Order under the Commiſſioners hands, as other Miniſters have, and that without the leaſt taking notice of his being ſent out by the Church at <hi>London.</hi> Theſe things are ſo clear, that himſelf cannot, and no man will with any face deny it. Now how Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> dares call this a falſe Charge, and ſo accuſe the whole Church at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> for ſaying that which ſo many know to be true, I much wonder; for I muſt in this particular clear the Church, and deeply blame him.</p>
                  <p>And for his ſaying he can ſhew my Letter to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate him in this, my Anſwer is, I known not how he may alter the words, or invert the ſenſe, but I here challenge him to produce ſuch a Letter from my hand as contradicts what I have here written, and I'll bear the blame; but he hath abuſed the Church and me, the Lord give him repentance. The truth of theſe things I affirm on my perſonal know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and ſubſcribe my name,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Tho. Weld.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Thirdly, he not onely abuſeth particular perſons, Mr. <hi>Weld,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> Mr. <hi>Eaton, Hugh Prichard,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:137293:16"/>but he lets fly againſt whole Churches, as <hi>the Church of Wrexam,</hi> which he accuſes of <hi>excisſive pride, groſs errour, envy at his perſon, prophaneſſe, ſtrange diſorder a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Baptiſm,</hi> and many other enormities among them, <hi>pag.</hi> 9, 10. And the Church at <hi>Newcaſtle, they are a company of rigid ones, falſe accuſers, violent,</hi> pag. 19, 20. And the Church at <hi>London, they deal irregularly, and hastily withdraw without giving him warning; they will not hear the truth, though not abundantly teſtified. So that their cenſure is null and void.</hi> Thus he proceeds to rage, and fight, and teare, and (like the drunken man in the <hi>Proverbs</hi>) to caſt fire-brands at all that ſtand in his way. Anſwer all his folly I will not, but this.</p>
            <p>Firſt: We have neither allowance from the Word or from Reaſon to beleeve one word of all theſe alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations againſt ſo many godly men; where is the <hi>mouth of two or three witneſſes?</hi> And if againſt an Elder onely without two or three witneſſes wee muſt not receive one accuſation, how dare we receive theſe, <hi>ſo manifold, deep, and hideous accuſations againſt whole Churches and Elders too?</hi> The Accuſer alſo being found no competent witneſſe, being in his <hi>hot blood, in a way of recrimination,</hi> and a <hi>known lyar,</hi> as hath been proved; therefore if he ſhould ſay ten times as much, it is all nothing without further proof.</p>
            <p>Secondly: What hee doth ſay againſt thoſe Churches, eſpecially that of <hi>Wrexam,</hi> is but a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming his malice and ignorance in Church-diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline: For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. He ſpends many words to declare, <hi>he was not excommunicate out of the Church of</hi> Wrexam, <hi>but that he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:137293:16"/>went out of himſelf, and proclaimed himſelf none of theirs.</hi> But let me ask this knowing man, if he ever learned from Chriſt, that a Member, when the Church is dealing with him, in order to a Cenſure, and he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the blow a comming, to award it off, withdraws himſelf, ſaying, he rejects the Church, and diſclaims them, and ſo they proceed againſt him for contempt, whether (I ſay) ſuch a one is not juſtly Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate, and whether ſuch a cenſure be not a reall and lawfull Cenſure? elſe any man, juſt before the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is denounced may withdraw, and ſo no man li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving need be Excommunicated; and then it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, Chriſt ordained that Cenſure in vain; yet in this ſilly, ſinfull ſhift he pleaſes himſelf, and deludes Babes with this pretence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Yea, but they are <hi>a very corrupt Church, and therefore their Cenſure is contemptible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. As before was ſaid, we dare not beleeve one word of all he ſaith out of Gods way.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If this that you ſay had been true, is this the way for you to reject them, and Excommunicate your ſelf? No, you ſhould firſt have cleared your ſelf of thoſe groſs things laid to your own charge.</p>
            <p>Secondly, humbly, and with all meckneſs have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented their diſorders to their conſideration.</p>
            <p n="3">3. You ſhould have endeavoured to convince them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And have waited with patience, <hi>if peradventure God would at any time have given them repentance.</hi> And then,</p>
            <p n="5">5. Deſired leave to referre the matter to other El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Churches, who might without prejudice, or partiality have weighed the ſtrength of what you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:137293:17"/>againſt them; and after all to have deſired leave in all humility to withdraw, in caſe no ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction could be had, and not to fling away diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when in a way of cenſure for your faults, and ſay, <hi>you renounce the Church.</hi> This is,
<list>
                  <item>1. Plain Schiſm.</item>
                  <item>2. Intollerable Pride.</item>
                  <item>3. Contempt of the Church.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Contempt of Chriſts Ordinances, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Chriſt himſelf the Inſtitutor of it, and (which makes all worſe) he ſtill juſtifies himſelf in all this. Beſides for a member to cut off it ſelf without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the body, is a thing unnatural and monſtrous, never heard of in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Secondly: He groſly abuſeth, and ſhamefully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpattered the Church at <hi>London</hi> in ſundry particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, but we ſee he can do no other. We ſhall obſerve but two or three things more, and conclude.</p>
            <p>Firſt: He tells you, in a vaunt, <hi>p.</hi> 14. <hi>he had not onely</hi> 80 <abbr>l.</abbr> per annum, <hi>but</hi> 40 <abbr>l.</abbr> per augmentation; but he tels you not withall, that this was before the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners wel knew him, &amp; that as ſoon as they ſaw his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and carriage with the ſame hands they gave him the Augmentation, they took it from him again, as judging him unworthy of it; and how that after it was gone, he crouched to the Commiſſioners, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuated fawningly to ſome of the Miniſters to get it regained, but it never could, and whether it was not one great cauſe of his leaving the North, I leave to be conſidered. Truly, ſome of us well know they never ſaw the Commiſſioners more aſhamed of ſetling any man than of his ſettlement at <hi>Hexam,</hi> and reſolved for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:137293:17"/>his ſake as long as they ſhould ſit, to know men better before they ſettled them, and never be ſo cheated by any mans gloſing and hypocritical pretences, as by his. But it was too late to repent after it was done.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He vaunts often in two or three of his Pamphlets, what a <hi>company of Saints, and precious people he had at</hi> Hexam, <hi>and how his Church flouriſhed;</hi> but tells you not of his tarrying there ſo long, that ſo few would come to hear him, that it was time to lay the key under the door, and give up.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He profeſſeth that he receives none to Baptiſm but ſuch as he judgeth to be <hi>pretious Saints;</hi> and yet it's proved againſt him, that he baptized ſome perſons at <hi>Stokesbey,</hi> and in <hi>Cheſhire, &amp;c.</hi> that made no profeſſion of their faith at all; and this himſelf grants, <hi>pag.</hi> 17. How can ſuch be known to be precious Saints? and how does this accord with <hi>John Baptiſts</hi> practice, who Baptized none but ſuch as <hi>made confeſsion of their ſins,</hi> Mat. 5. or <hi>Philips</hi> practice, who requires the Eunuch to <hi>confeſs his faith,</hi> Acts 8.37? But this man (it ſeems) dares <hi>ſay</hi> any thing, or <hi>do</hi> any thing; 'tis no new thing to hear him contradicting the practice of others, or his own principles. But to what end doe I waſte Ink and Paper in anſwering him, whom I have ſo little hopes to reclaim? I will therefore turn the ſtream into another chanel, and by way of Concluſion di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect my ſpeech to thoſe plain-hearted, well-meaning Chriſtians miſled by him in the Town of <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> and elſwhere.</p>
            <p>You <hi>Colcheſter</hi> Chriſtians and others, that have lent your ears to this Seedſman of Sedition, and happily think, that in entertaining this Stranger, you have
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:137293:18"/>entertained an Angel of God, doe but a little view his face in this glaſs, and ſee if his countenance be like that of an Angel. Is he not here plainly convicted of boaſting, lying, ſlandering, and many other ſin? Has he not for theſe crimes been taxed by faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and cenſured by whole Churches, and is all this nothing? Can you expect a bleſſing from the God of Heaven while you harbour ſuch a one in your boſoms as he hath ſealed up under a ſpiritual judgement, with which (as a rod at his back) he ranges up and down the world, and is not humbled, but rather hardened by it? Take heed you bring not the guilt of his ſin on your own heads; For (I call God to witneſſe) 'tis not the man, but his ſin I all along ſtrike at; and a ſin both fouly practiced, and fully proved againſt him, the horrid ſin of <hi>Lying</hi> (among many other) a ſin ſo <hi>hatefull to God,</hi> Prov. 12.22. yea ſo <hi>loathſome</hi> in the very noſtrils of Nature, that among the ſavage <hi>Indians,</hi> he that told a lye thrice, was condemned to perpetual ſilence, if <hi>Aelian</hi> may be credited; this is (it ſeems by his own confeſſion in his book) the grand crime for which Mr. <hi>Tillam</hi> ſtands Excommunicate; for which I ſhall not need to judge him, two Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches having already paſſed ſentence upon him, guided (I ſuppoſe) by that rule of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.34. <hi>Out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh;</hi> as the Phyſician looking on the ſick mans <hi>tongue,</hi> when hee ſees that foul, concludes it is <hi>worſe within.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(Chriſtians) let me deal a little with your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; doe you take the word of Chriſt for your rule? How then dare you hear him that will not hear the Church? Or by what Scripture-ground can you take
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:137293:18"/>him for your Paſtor, whom you are to look upon as a Heathen or a Publican? And that by expreſs war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. Yea let me ask you further, how unlikely is it, that he ſhould be to you a Preacher of <hi>truth,</hi> who has been rejected by others as a venter of <hi>falſhood?</hi> Indeed what has he to doe to take Gods covenant into hismouth, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to be reformed? And how unfit is he to be a Preacher, whom the Churches of Chriſt have judged unfit to be a Member? What Truths he has Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched among you, I know not; but if he has ſpoken to you the words of Truth and Soberneſſe, he is both much manded ſince he left the North, and miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by ſome of eminent note in the South, who have affirmed, and will maintain it to his face, that he has dealt moſt unfaithfully in ſome of the <hi>main truths</hi> of the Goſpel, as, <hi>denying Infants to be guilty of Original ſin till they come to act ſin,</hi> and affirming, <hi>that we are not juſtified by the ſame juſtifying Faith that</hi> Luther <hi>and the firſt Reformers were juſtified by</hi> (to ſay nothing of his <hi>new Ordinances, new Sacraments, new Sabbath,</hi> that he contends for) theſe are no ſmall and petty Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</p>
            <p>The good Lord open your eyes that you may ſee the evill of thoſe dangerous Principles he has ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered among you: And let me beſeech you, in the bowels of Chriſt (as a well-wiſher to your ſouls, though a ſtranger to your perſons) that you would take heed of being carried about with theſe divers and ſtrange doctrines, yea with any one of them: For if Satan can but draw you into one, hee will quickly lead you into all. He that ſaith <hi>yea</hi> to the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:137293:19"/>Devill in a little, ſhall not ſay him <hi>nay</hi> when he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. In the fear of God I beſeech you conſider how you will be able to look Chriſt in the face another day, when your own Conſciences will tell you, you have parted with his Truths upon the bare word of a branded Lyar. My record is on high, that I have not written theſe few lines out of envy, ſpleen, or paſſion, but out of pitty and compaſſion to your ſouls: Read all before you cenſure; compare Mr. <hi>Tillam's</hi> Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet with theſe Papers, and I ſuppoſe he will be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently anſwered, and all ſober-minded Chriſtians abundantly ſatisfied.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="list_of_principles">
            <pb facs="tcp:137293:19"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of many pernicious Principles and falſe Doctrines, publiquely in the Pulpit, and elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where aſſerted by Mr. <hi>Tho: Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam</hi> in the Town of <hi>Colchester.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>FIrſt: That we are not juſtified by the ſame juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Faith that our Forefathers were justified by.</item>
               <item>Secondly: That Antichriſt ſhall not be deſtroyed till Christs perſonal appearing the ſecond time in the fleſh, &amp; that whoever teacheth otherwiſe is a deluder.</item>
               <item>Thirdly: That children are not guiltie of original ſin till they act ſin.</item>
               <item>Fourthly: That Love-feasts, waſhing the Diſciples feet, the Holy kiſs, and Annointing the Sick with oyl, are Ordinances ſtill to be obſerved in the Churches of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>Fifthly: That the Lord Chriſt was a Carpenter, but neither Houſe, nor Ship-Carpenter, but a Yoke-maker; to prove which he cited, <hi>Mat. 11.29.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sixthly: That thoſe whom he layes his hands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and bleſſes, are as really bleſſed, as thoſe whom
<pb facs="tcp:137293:20"/>Chriſt bleſſed when he was upon earth.</item>
               <item>Seventhly: That Baptizing in the Name of the Eather, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, as ſo far from being the ſubſtantial form of Baptiſm, that it is ſcarce a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance in Baptiſm.</item>
               <item>Eightly: That there is none truly called to the Miniſtry, but by Viſions Dreams. Revelations, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from Heaven.</item>
               <item>Ninthly: That not any Infant-Baptiſm is of God.</item>
               <item>Tenthly: That the Firſt day of the week is not our Chriſtian Sabbath.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe things can be proved againſt him, by divers witneſſes to each.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
